<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Article Authoring DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "dtd/JATS-articleauthoring1.dtd">
<article>
  <front>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Inconsistent XML as a barrier to reuse of Open Access Content</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mietchen</surname>
            <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff>Museum für Naturkunde - Leibniz-Institut für Evolutions- und Biodiversitätsforschung,
            Berlin, Germany</aff>
          <aff>Open Knowledge Foundation, Berlin, Germany</aff>
          <bio>
            <p>Daniel Mietchen is a biophysicist and a consultant to Open Access publishers on
              matters of publishing technology, including XML-based workflows.</p>
          </bio>
        </contrib>
        <contrib>
          <name>
            <surname>Maloney</surname>
            <given-names>Chris</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff>PMC/NCBI/NIH, Bethesda, MD</aff>
          <bio>
            <p>Chris Maloney is a web developer working for NCBI’s PMC and Bookshelf resources. He
              has worked with XML technologies for over ten years.</p>
          </bio>
        </contrib>
        <contrib>
          <name>
            <surname>Moskopp</surname>
            <given-names>Nils Dagsson</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff>?</aff>
          <bio>
            <p>Nils Dagsson Moskopp is a philosophy student, blogger and programmer with focus on
              web development.</p>
          </bio>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>

      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>
          The authors assert themselves as the copyright holders of this paper.
        </copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>D. Mietchen, C. Maloney, N. Moskopp</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>The copyright holder grants the U.S. National Library of Medicine permission to
            archive and post a copy of this paper on the Journal Article Tag Suite Conference
            proceedings website.</license-p>
        </license>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p> This work is licensed under a <ext-link
              xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution
              3.0 Unported License</ext-link>. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>


      <abstract abstract-type="brief">
        <p>In this paper, we will describe the current state of some of the tagging of articles
          within the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/tools/openftlist/">PMC Open Access
            subset</ext-link>. As a case study, we will use our experiences developing the <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/erlehmann/open-access-media-importer"
            >Open Access Media Importer</ext-link>, a tool to harvest content from the OA subset for
          automated upload to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Uploaded_with_Open_Access_Media_Importer"
            >Wikimedia Commons</ext-link>.</p>
        <p>Tagging inconsistencies stretch across several aspects of the articles, ranging from
          licensing to keywords to the media types of supplementary materials. While all of these
          complicate large-scale reuse, the unclear licensing statements had the greatest impact,
          requiring us to implement text mining-like algorithms in order to accurately determine
          whether or not specific content was compatible with reuse on Wikimedia Commons.</p>
        <p>Besides presenting examples of incorrectly tagged XML from a range of publishers, we will
          also explore past and current efforts towards standardization of license tagging, and we
          will describe a set of recommendations related to tagging practices of certain data, to
          ensure that it is both compatible with existing standards, and consistent and
          machine-readable.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>

  <body>
    <sec id='intro'>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <sec id='scope'>
        <title>Scope of this paper</title>
        <p>The aim of this paper is to describe the problems that we came across when attempting to
          reuse materials from the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/tools/openftlist/">PMC Open Access
            Subset</ext-link> in an automated fashion and at scale. Some of the issues are specific
          to certain kinds of content, others are a barrier to reuse more generally. Some of them
          are specific to individual articles, journals or publishers, while others apply more
          widely.</p>
        <p>In discussing these issues, we take the perspective of a re-user of JATS-conveyed
          content, conscious of the possibility that the perspectives of producers and curators of
          this content and of maintainers of JATS standards may differ. We conclude with a series of
          recommendations that would have facilitated the implementation of our reuse project and
          that could serve as the basis for a discussion on how to facilitate reuse more
          generally.</p>
      </sec>

      <sec id='oami'>
        <title>The Open Access Media Importer</title>
        <p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Open_Access_Media_Importer_Bot">Open
            Access Media Importer</ext-link> is an automated bot, developed with <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="https://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/User:OpenScientist/Open_grant_writing/Wissenswert_2011"
            >initial support</ext-link> from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.wikimedia.de/wiki/Hauptseite">Wikimedia Deutschland</ext-link>,
          that harvests multimedia content from open access repositories, and uploads that content
          to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/">Wikimedia
            Commons</ext-link>, the media repository used by the Wikipedias and their sister
          project. Once in Wikimedia Commons, those multimedia files are very easy to insert into
          Wikipedia pages, and to be reused on a wide variety of other wikis and Wikimedia
          projects.</p>
        <p>Currently, the OAMI harvests content from the PMC Open Access Subset. Since most articles
          in the subset are actually not Open Access (in the sense of being free to reuse, revise,
          remix and redistribute), the bot scans the XML sources of new articles and reads the
          license information in order to determine those that are. It then checks whether these
          have multimedia files in their supplementary materials. If so, they are downloaded,
          converted and uploaded to Wikimedia Commons along with the available metadata. At the time
          of writing, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Uploaded_with_Open_Access_Media_Importer"
            >over 13,000 multimedia files</ext-link> had been processed this way. Figure 1
          illustrates the timeline of uploads per day from the OAMI to Wikimedia Commons, from its
          inception up to the present time.</p>
        <fig id="fig1">
          <caption>
            <title>Figure 1. Daily uploads by the Open Access Media Importer to Wikimedia Commons
              between July 2012 and September 2013.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="OAMI-uploads.png"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>

    <sec id='license-tagging'>
      <title>License tagging</title>
      <p>As mentioned above, an important function of the OAMI is to determine, for each media file,
        the license under which it or its parent article has been released.</p>
      <p>In reading and analyzing the license data, the OAMI looks for licenses that are truly open,
        in the sense of being free to reuse, revise, remix and redistribute, as laid out in the
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://www.budapestopenaccessinitiative.org/read">Budapest Open Access
          Initiative</ext-link> a decade ago. Licenses with &quot;non-commercial&quot; and &quot;no
        derivatives&quot; clauses are <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Commons:Licensing">not
          acceptable</ext-link> on Wikimedia Commons. Figure 2 shows a breakdown of the licenses we
        have found in the PMC OA subset for articles indexed during the first week of May this year,
        with color-coding to illustrate which licenses are &quot;free&quot; in the sense of allowing
        reuse on Wikimedia Commons, and which are not. More formal definitions of this sense of
        freedom can be found in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://freedomdefined.org/">Definition of Free Cultural Works</ext-link> and
        the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://opendefinition.org/">Open
          Definition</ext-link>.</p>
      <fig id="fig2">
        <caption>
          <title>Figure 2. Licenses of supplementary materials in the PMC OA subset, by license URI,
            for the first week of May 2013.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="licenses.png"/>
      </fig>
      <p>This information is tagged in the source XML for each article. In the rest of this section,
        we will review the JATS elements and attributes related to license data, and then describe
        some of the problems we encountered when trying to harvest this data from actual
        articles.</p>
      <p>In JATS 1.0, there are several XML elements and attributes that are used to specify license
        information for an article and its accompanying multimedia files.</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?elem=permissions"
              >&lt;permissions&gt;</ext-link> - this is a container element, within which all
            copyright and license metadata should appear</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?elem=license"
              >&lt;license&gt;</ext-link> - this is the main element for specifying license
            information. Among the attributes allowed on this element, the following two are
            relevant:</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?attr=license-type"
              >@license-type</ext-link> - the value is not constrained; &quot;open-access&quot; is
            one suggested value.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?attr=xlink:href"
              >@xlink:href</ext-link> - takes an external URL; often the URL identifying the
            specific Creative Commons license.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?elem=license-p"
              >&lt;license-p&gt;</ext-link> - paragraph of text within a &lt;license&gt; element.
            Semantically, this is a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?elem=p"
              >&lt;p&gt;</ext-link> element with the addition of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?elem=price"
              >&lt;price&gt;</ext-link> to the content model. (Prior to the NLM Tag Set version 3.0,
            the &lt;p&gt; element was used here.)</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?elem=ext-link"
              >&lt;ext-link&gt;</ext-link> - can appear within the &lt;license-p&gt; element, and
            provides a link to an external resource. This also takes an optional xlink:href
            attribute.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <p>An example of good license tagging, from the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?elem=license">JATS 1.0 Tag
          Library documentation</ext-link>, is the following.</p>

      <preformat>&lt;permissions&gt;
  ...
  &lt;license license-type=&quot;open-access&quot;
           xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/&quot;&gt;
    &lt;license-p&gt;This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
      Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
      distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original
      work is properly cited.&lt;/license-p&gt;
  &lt;/license&gt;
&lt;/permissions&gt;</preformat>
      <p>In the above example, the Creative Commons license is unambiguously identified by the URI
        in the @xlink:href attribute of the &lt;license&gt; element. The &lt;license-p&gt; element
        provides the human-readable text of the license, which matches the machine-readable version
        (except for not including the version number of the Creative Commons license, and the
        hyperlink.)</p>
      <p>
        <bold>
          <italic>PMC Tagging Guidelines and Style Checker</italic>
        </bold>
      </p>
      <p>PMC provides additional recommendations and specifications for article tagging, which are
        layered on top of the requirements of the JATS standard. These are documented at the
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/tagging-guidelines/article/style.html"
          >PMC Tagging Guidelines</ext-link>, and they include guidelines for tagging <ext-link
          ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/tagging-guidelines/article/dobs.html#dob-license"
          >license information</ext-link>.</p>
      <p>Recently, in part in order to minimize some of the inconsistencies in tagging that are
        described below, PMC has amended these to include the following statement:</p>
      <disp-quote>
        <p>When including a URI for a license, the URI should be included either on the
          &lt;license&gt; in @xlink:href (preferred) or in an &lt;ext-link&gt; in the content of the
          license. The URI must not be tagged in both places.</p>
      </disp-quote>
      <p>Complementing that, the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/tools/stylechecker/">Style Checker</ext-link>
        now has additional checks to help ensure the consistency of the license information. In
        particular, it will generate an error if there is an xlink:href attribute on the
        &lt;license&gt; element, and one on a descendent &lt;ext-link&gt; element, and the URIs do
        not match.</p>
      <p>Unfortunately, these recent changes do little to address most of the problems described in
        this paper. We provide some recommendations for how these resources could be further
        improved, in the <xref rid='recommendations'>Recommendations</xref> section, below.</p>


      <sec id='license-problems'>
        <title>Problems encountered by the bot</title>
        <p>While developing and deploying the OAMI, we discovered that automatically discerning the
          licensing terms and reuse rights was non-trivial.  In contrast to the example of
          &quot;good&quot; markup above, within the article XML available from the PMC OA subset,
          licensing metadata is not expressed consistently across journals, and sometimes not even
          across different articles of the same journal.  Here, we list a few examples.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Contradictory information</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>In many cases, the URI identifying the Creative Commons license was contradicted by the
          human-readable text.  For example, from the article <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC2658715"
            >PMC2658715</ext-link> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1471-4159.2008.05520.x/abstract"
            >publisher version</ext-link>), the URI specifies &quot;CC-BY&quot;, but the
          human-readable description adds the extra &quot;NC&quot; (non-commercial) restriction:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;license license-type=&quot;open-access&quot;
         xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Re-use of this article is permitted in accordance with the Creative Commons Deed,
    Attribution 2.5, which does not permit commercial exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/license&gt;</preformat>
        <p>In other examples, the human-readable descriptions were actually self-contradictory. The
          following is an example from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3143982"
            >PMC3143982</ext-link> that also has a typo in the license name.</p>
        <preformat>&lt;license license-type=&quot;open-access&quot;&gt;
  &lt;license-p&gt;This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attr0ibution 3.0 License
    (by-nc 3.0).&lt;/license-p&gt;
  ...
&lt;/license&gt;</preformat>
        <p>We have found that the phenomenon of self-contradictory licenses is rather common and not
          restricted to small and lesser known publishers. The next example is from <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3468739/"
            >PMC3468739</ext-link>. While the machine-readable license is CC BY, the human-readable
          version has a non-commercial clause.</p>
        <preformat>&lt;license license-type=&quot;open-access&quot;
         xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/&quot;&gt;
  &lt;license-p&gt;Re-use of this article is permitted in accordance with the Creative
    Commons Deed, Attribution 2.5, which does not permit commercial
    exploitation.&lt;/license-p&gt;
&lt;/license&gt;</preformat>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>License information outside the &lt;license&gt; element</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>In the following example, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3158088/"
            >PMC3158088</ext-link>, the Creative Commons license text is given in the
          &lt;copyright-statement&gt; element rather than the &lt;license&gt; element.</p>
        <preformat>&lt;permissions&gt;
  &lt;copyright-statement&gt;
    Uosaki et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of
    the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
    distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author
    and source are credited.
  &lt;/copyright-statement&gt;
  &lt;copyright-year&gt;2011&lt;/copyright-year&gt;
&lt;/permissions&gt;</preformat>
        <p>These statements in the &lt;copyright-statement&gt; element may (<ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3143982PMC3605902/"
            >PMC3605902</ext-link>) or may not (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3143982PMC3589467/"
            >PMC3589467</ext-link>) contain an xlink:href attribute, even within otherwise identical
          license text.</p>
        <p>At the time of this writing, PMC has <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/?term=%22author+manuscript%22%5Bfilter%5D"
            >281,148 author manuscripts</ext-link>, of which <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/?term=%22author+manuscript%22%5Bfilter%5D+AND+%22open+access%22%5Bfilter%5D"
            >5383</ext-link> (about 2%) are in the OA subset. In a sample of those that are not in
          the OA subset, it was found that 1%, do in fact have a Creative Commons license, but the
          license information is completely outside of the &lt;permissions&gt; element. For example,
          in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3143982PMC3717328/"
            >PMC3717328</ext-link>, the license information is given in a &lt;fn&gt; element within
          the back matter:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;fn id=&quot;FN5&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p content-type=&quot;publisher-disclaimer&quot;&gt;
    &lt;bold&gt;Open Access&lt;/bold&gt;: This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative
    Commons Attribution License 3.0 which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in
    any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited. To view a copy of
    the license, visit &lt;ext-link ext-link-type=&quot;uri&quot;
      xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&quot;
    &gt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&lt;/ext-link&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/fn&gt;</preformat>
        <p>This effectively makes it undiscoverable, because any automatic process attempting to
          determine the license of an article would have to exclude things outside of the
          &lt;permissions&gt; element, otherwise there would be the possibility of false positives
          resulting from articles that <italic>discuss</italic> and <italic>quote</italic> licenses
          and license text within the article body.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Contradictory URIs</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>Until recently, many articles in PMC had mismatches between the URIs that appear on the
          &lt;license&gt; element and those that appear inside the license text within
          &lt;ext-link&gt; elements. To address this problem, as mentioned above, PMC has instituted
          a new Style Checker rule that requires that if there are multiple URIs, they must
          match.</p>
        <p>In addition, PMC has fixed most instances of such conflicts within the existing
          database.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>No machine-readable URI</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>Some articles (including the vast majority of those deposited by PLOS) have Creative
          Commons licenses, but don't contain any machine-readable URI identifying that license. An
          example of the tagging from a recent PLOS ONE article, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3738584/"
            >PMC3738584</ext-link>, is:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;permissions&gt;
  &lt;copyright-year&gt;2013&lt;/copyright-year&gt;
  &lt;copyright-holder&gt;Bassaneze et al&lt;/copyright-holder&gt;
  &lt;license&gt;
    &lt;license-p&gt;This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
      Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
      distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author
      and source are credited.&lt;/license-p&gt;
  &lt;/license&gt;
&lt;/permissions&gt;</preformat>
        <p>This is particularly troubling, since PLOS papers represent a large and quickly
          increasing percentage of PMC, and especially PMC's OA content. Additionally, the phrasing
          of the human-readable text may vary across articles from the same journal that are under
          the same license.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Missing license information altogether</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>Finally, there are the cases of articles in the OA subset (e.g. <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3775889/"
            >PMC3775889</ext-link>) that have no license information in the XML at all, meaning that
          an automated tool would either have to consider the article to be under &quot;all rights
          reserved&quot; – which would even prohibit the kind of data mining that the OA subset is
          intended for and that the OAMI performs – or to contain code specific to particular
          journals or publishers, or require manual assistance by a human (who, in the case of the
          cited example, would find out that the article in question is <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://currents.plos.org/genomictests/terms-of-use/"
            >actually licensed CC BY</ext-link>).</p>


      </sec>
      <sec id='impact-on-pmc'>
        <title>Impact of these problems on PMC</title>
        <p>PMC recently implemented a search-by-license feature, described on their <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/tools/openftlist/">Open
            Access Subset</ext-link> page. This feature allows users to query for articles matching
          specific Creative Commons licenses, and can be combined with other search terms.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, because of the tagging problems described above, the PMC indexer, in many
          cases, cannot correctly determine the license of articles. Therefore, the search result
          sets are much smaller than they otherwise would be.</p>
        <p>For example, in a sample of 100 articles that are in the OA subset, but that do not match
          the &quot;cc license&quot; filter (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/?term=%22open+access%22%5Bfilter%5D+NOT+%22cc+license%22%5Bfilter%5D"
            >PMC search</ext-link>), it was found that 99 did, in fact, have CC licenses, but that
          tagging problems prevented them from being correctly identified as such. At the time of
          this writing, there were 663,843 articles in the OA subset, and 52% did not match the
          &quot;cc license&quot; filter. If the sample described above is representative, then that
          means about 340,000 eligible articles would not be discoverable through this search
          feature.</p>


      </sec>
      <sec id='impact-beyond-pmc'>
        <title>Impact of these problems beyond PMC</title>
        <p>In the OAMI, these problems necessitated the development of a fairly sophisticated
          text-mining module that examined both the machine-readable URI in the &lt;license&gt;
          element, as well as the human-readable expressions, so as to determine the publisher's
          intent. Because of Wikimedia Commons' strict enforcement of proper licensing, it was
          important that this module be conservative:  false positives being much less acceptable
          than false negatives.</p>
        <p>Development of a license-mining algorithm such as this is costly, and would tax the
          resources of any project seeking to reuse PMC OA content. Even with this algorithm, the
          inconsistency and number of errors that we found indicate that there are still a great
          number of articles that could legitimately be uploaded to Wikimedia Commons, but that are
          not properly identified. This does a disservice to those who released their material with
          reuse-friendly licenses, often in the hopes of having it be used as widely as
          possible.</p>
        <p>The lack of ability to reliably determine licensing information on a per-article basis
          contributes to other problems as well. One such problem is that publishers sometimes erect
          paywalls around open access content, counter to the express wishes of the authors. One way
          to explain this could be that the sites are not flexible enough to handle per-issue or
          per-article license information. Perhaps, if the tagging of this information in JATS XML
          documents were consistent and reliable, it would facilitate systems that were more
          flexible, and able to serve open content directly, which still presenting a paywall for
          closed content.</p>
        <p>As another example, the Directory of Open Access Journals (DOAJ) already allows one to
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.doaj.org/doaj?func=byLicense">list
            journals by license</ext-link>, and plans are afoot to expand this functionality to the
          level of individual articles. Again, this could be facilitated by consistent and reliable
          tagging of JATS XML articles.</p>


      </sec>
      <sec id='broader-issues'>
        <title>Broader license issues</title>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Multiple licenses with different scope</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>Recently, some journals have begun to make data and supplementary materials available
          under a license that differs from the main article's license. For example, F1000Research
          is providing articles with text content that is available under CC-BY, but with
          accompanying data available in the public domain (CC0). Here is an example of the tagging
          of a recent article from their website:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;permissions&gt;
  &lt;copyright-statement&gt;Copyright: © 2013 Baird AH et al.&lt;/copyright-statement&gt;
  &lt;copyright-year&gt;2013&lt;/copyright-year&gt;
  &lt;license license-type=&quot;open-access&quot;
           xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&quot;&gt;
    &lt;license-p&gt;This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the
      Creative Commons Attribution Licence, which permits unrestricted use,
      distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
      properly cited.&lt;/license-p&gt;
  &lt;/license&gt;
  &lt;license license-type=&quot;open-access&quot;
           xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/&quot;&gt;
    &lt;license-p&gt;Data associated with the article are available under the terms of
      the Creative Commons Zero &quot;No rights reserved&quot; data waiver (CC0 1.0 Public
      domain dedication).&lt;/license-p&gt;
  &lt;/license&gt;
&lt;/permissions&gt;</preformat>
        <p>The scope and the intent of each of the two &lt;license&gt; elements is clear to a human
          reader, but, unfortunately, there is no way for an automated bot to be able to
          unambiguously identify the two different scopes.</p>
        <p>If licensing information were available along with provenance on a per-file basis in a
          machine-readable format, there would be potential for automated checks of licensing
          information. Few scholars outside the field of copyright law are aware of all the
          implications of publishing under certain licenses, which sometimes leads to content
          available under a particular license being published (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.plosone.org/annotation/listThread.action?root=60001">Example
            1</ext-link>) or re-published (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.plosbiology.org/annotation/listThread.action?root=53679">Example
            2</ext-link>) in incompatibly licensed papers. In Example 1, the issue could be solved
          by the copyright holder changing the licensing of the original file, whereas in Example 2,
          a video displaying wrong license information was fixed and re-uploaded at the publisher's
          site but <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3485268/bin/pone.0046962.s003.mp4"
            >not at PMC</ext-link>, despite the published correction.</p>
        <p>There is no straightforward way to detect such cases algorithmically, and raising
          awareness for these issues amongst authors, editors and reviewers can certainly not be
          automated either.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Incremental licenses</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>Often, articles are published with license terms that change over time. The following is
          an example from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.cgi?db=pmc&amp;id=3601365"
            >PMC3601365</ext-link>.</p>
        <preformat>&lt;license license-type=&quot;openaccess&quot;&gt;
  &lt;license-p&gt;
    This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share
    Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date
    (see &lt;ext-link ext-link-type=&quot;uri&quot;
      xlink:href=&quot;http://www.rupress.org/terms&quot;&gt;http://www.rupress.org/terms&lt;/ext-link&gt;).
    After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License
    (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, as described at
    &lt;ext-link ext-link-type=&quot;uri&quot;
      xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/&quot;&gt;
    http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/&lt;/ext-link&gt;).
  &lt;/license-p&gt;
&lt;/license&gt;</preformat>
        <p>One problem with this is that both licenses are given within a single &lt;license&gt;
          element, which would complicate the data model for any program attempting to process
          these. Another is that there is no machine-readable indication of the time period covered
          by each of the two separate licenses.</p>
        <p>We provide a recommendation of how this tagging could be improved (both for licenses with
          different scope, and with different effective date ranges) in &quot;PMC license
          metadata&quot;, below.</p>


      </sec>
      <sec id='license-standards'>
        <title>Standardization efforts</title>
        <p>There have been a number of efforts to standardize the expression of license metadata.
          Among these are:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/ns">Creative
                Commons Rights Expression Language</ext-link> (CC-REL)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.editeur.org/21/ONIX-PL/">ONIX
                for Publications Licenses</ext-link> (ONIX-PL)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Ongoing <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                xlink:href="http://www.niso.org/news/pr/view?item_key=d2e5f409bc6af6b7f504a10edf0329203ffec6f9"
                >NISO Initiative to Develop Standard for Open Access Metadata and
                Indicators</ext-link></p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Open_Access/Signalling_OA-ness"
                >Wikipedia: Signalling OA-ness</ext-link></p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Many of these standards provide complex mechanisms for specifying or customizing the
          particular terms of a license. We welcome these efforts, and look forward to the time when
          the tags they define can be integrated with JATS. However, the simplest and most
          fundamental way of robustly signalling a license will probably always be to unambiguously
          link to a URI that's defined, controlled and perhaps versioned by an established
          organization such as Creative Commons.</p>



      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id='media-types'>
      <title>Media types</title>
      <p>In addition to the problems with communicating the licensing terms, the media types of
        supplementary materials are frequently not indicated properly, which reduces discoverability
        and translates into extra efforts before any reuse becomes possible.</p>
      <p>Media types (originally called &quot;MIME types&quot;) are two part identifiers that
        describe the format of a multimedia file. Familiar examples are &quot;text/plain&quot;, and
        &quot;application/xml&quot;. When serving these types of files, web servers provide the
        media type in the HTTP &quot;Content-type&quot; header. This allows the client to determine
        how the file should be processed. In the case of the OAMI, the processing is the conversion
        of the file format, since Wikimedia Commons only accepts audio or video files encoded in
        open formats.</p>
      <p>The JATS standard provides two attributes to allow for encoding the media types of files
        that accompany journal articles:</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?attr=mimetype"
              >mimetype</ext-link></p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?attr=mime-subtype"
              >mime-subtype</ext-link></p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <p>These attributes are allowed on several elements that identify these types of files,
        including <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?elem=supplementary-material"
          >&lt;supplementary-material&gt;</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?elem=media"
          >&lt;media&gt;</ext-link>.</p>
      <p>The JATS specification includes the following example of how to tag a media file in an
        article's supplementary material (slightly elided):</p>
      <preformat>&lt;supplementary-material id=&quot;S1&quot; xlink:href=&quot;1471-2105-1-1-s1.pdf&quot;
                        mimetype=&quot;application/pdf&quot;&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supplementary PDF file supplied by authors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;/supplementary-material&gt;</preformat>
      <p>Note:</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p>The mimetype attribute is used to store both parts of the media type, rather than
            splitting out the &quot;subtype&quot; into the mime-subtype attribute</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>The information about the media file is given right on the
            &lt;supplementary-material&gt; element, rather than, for example, a child &lt;media&gt;
            element.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <p>In contrast, the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/tagging-guidelines/article/tags.html#el-suppl"
          >PMC Tagging Guidelines</ext-link> stipulate, for the &lt;supplementary-material&gt;
        element:</p>
      <disp-quote>
        <p>Should include &lt;media&gt; or &lt;graphic&gt; to identify the supplemental file. File
          description in &lt;media&gt; or &lt;graphic&gt; must include the file name (including file
          extension) in @xlink:href; &lt;media&gt; also requires @mime-type [sic], and
          @mime-subtype.</p>
      </disp-quote>
      <p>So, there is some ambiguity as to the best practice for tagging supplementary media
        files.</p>


      <sec id='mt-problems'>
        <title>Media type and related problems</title>
        <p>The following are some examples of the problems that we encountered that are related to
          media types.</p>
        <p>Foremost were those resulting from mismatches among:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>The declared media type in the @mimetype and @mime-subtype attributes of the source
              XML, including mismatches between the XML available from the publisher and PMC,</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>The &quot;Content-type&quot; headers as seen from PMC, and</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>The actual media type of the file.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Mismatches between publisher XML, PMC XML, and Content-type</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>The following figure suggests the scope of the problem of media type mismatches.</p>
        <fig id="fig3">
          <caption>
            <title>Figure 3. Supplementary media files with the wrong media type, by DOI prefix,
              from a sample of articles indexed in the first week of May 2013. Unknown refers to MS
              Office files, between the different formats of which we did not distinguish.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mediatype-mismatches-by-publisher.png"
          />
        </fig>
        <p>For an example of such a mismatch, in the article <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3162007/"
            >PMC3162007</ext-link>, the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3162007/bin/pone.0023819.s009.rar"
            >Models S1</ext-link> file under &quot;Supporting Information&quot; is actually of type
          &quot;application/x-rar-compressed&quot;. The original <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.plosone.org/article/fetchObjectAttachment.action?uri=info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0023819&amp;representation=XML"
            >publisher XML</ext-link> encodes this correctly:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;supplementary-material id=&quot;pone.0023819.s009&quot; mimetype=&quot;application/x-rar-compressed&quot; ...</preformat>
        <p>However, the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3162007"
            >XML from PMC</ext-link> is wrong:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;supplementary-material content-type=&quot;local-data&quot; id=&quot;pone.0023819.s009&quot;&gt;
  ...
  &lt;media xlink:href=&quot;pone.0023819.s009.rar&quot; mimetype=&quot;audio&quot; mime-subtype=&quot;x-realaudio&quot;&gt;
  ...</preformat>
        <p>Furthermore, PMC returns the (wrong) HTTP &quot;Content-Type&quot; header
          &quot;application/octet-stream&quot;.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Mismatches between filename extension and media type</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>In the article <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC2386968/"
            >PMC2386968</ext-link>, the URL to the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC2386968/bin/pone.0002276.s002.doc"
            >Movie S2</ext-link> ends with &quot;.doc&quot;, and PMC returns &quot;Content-Type:
          application/msword&quot;. However, the file is actually a Microsoft ASF file, which should
          have media type &quot;video/x-ms-wmv&quot;.</p>
        <p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC2386968"
            >PMC XML</ext-link> is wrong:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;supplementary-material content-type=&quot;local-data&quot; id=&quot;pone.0002276.s002&quot;&gt;
  ...
  &lt;media xlink:href=&quot;pone.0002276.s002.doc&quot; mimetype=&quot;application&quot; mime-subtype=&quot;msword&quot;&gt;
  ...</preformat>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Media type misidentified in publisher XML</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>In the article <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3619089/"
            >PMC3619089</ext-link>, the additional data file is a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3619089/bin/Movie_1.MP4"
            >video</ext-link> that has an actual media type of &quot;video/mp4&quot;, but this is
          tagged incorrectly in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.frontiersin.org/Journal/DownloadFile.ashx?xml=1&amp;FileId=15567&amp;articleId=41661&amp;Version=1&amp;ContentTypeId=22&amp;FileName=Finalxml.xml&amp;JournalAbbr=fnbot&amp;JournalSeqNo=00005&amp;JournalVolume=07"
            >publisher’s XML</ext-link> (notice the misspelling):</p>
        <preformat>&lt;supplementary-material xlink:href=&quot;Movie_1.MP4&quot; id=&quot;SM1&quot; mimetype=&quot;applicationn/MP4&quot; ...</preformat>
        <p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3619089"
            >PMC XML</ext-link> is wrong too, but in a different way:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;supplementary-material content-type=&quot;local-data&quot; id=&quot;SM1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;media xlink:href=&quot;Movie_1.MP4&quot; mimetype=&quot;video&quot; mime-subtype=&quot;quicktime&quot;&gt;
  ...</preformat>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Missing media type in XML</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>Many articles lack any indication of the media type within their XML. For example, in the
          article <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3765204/"
            >PMC3765204</ext-link>, there is no media type indicated for either Movie 1 or Movie 2.
          The two videos in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3770602/"
            >PMC3770602</ext-link> also lack any indication of media type.</p>
        <p>The problem of missing @mimetype and @mime-subtype attributes is fairly common. For
          example, in the article <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3765681/"
            >PMC3765681</ext-link>, the XML lacks any indication of the media type:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;media xlink:href=&quot;1556-276X-8-131-S1.tiff&quot;&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click here for file&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;/media&gt;</preformat>
        <p>After September, 2013, when PMC stopped writing these attributes into source XML (see
          <xref rid='mt-pmc-efforts'>Recent efforts at PMC</xref>, below) the frequency of this problem went up, but the
          frequency of incorrect attribute values went down, as would be expected.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Problems with &lt;label&gt;, &lt;caption&gt; and &lt;title&gt;</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>In addition to problems involving the media types, there is also a lot of variability in
          the way that the &lt;label&gt;, &lt;caption&gt; and &lt;title&gt; elements are used, and
          this causes problems for automated tools.</p>
        <p>For instance, in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3713652"
            >PMC3713652</ext-link>, the caption for several supplementary files is given in the
          first caption element, and there is no way to automate the process of determining which
          caption should go with which file:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;supplementary-material content-type=&quot;local-data&quot; id=&quot;f1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;
    ...
    &lt;p&gt;Supplemental Figure 1. Micrographs illustrating ...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supplemental Figure 2. Merged image of RANKL, FN, ...&lt;/p&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;media xlink:href=&quot;876316.f1.avi&quot; mimetype=&quot;video&quot; mime-subtype=&quot;x-msvideo&quot;&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click here for additional data file.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;/media&gt;
&lt;/supplementary-material&gt;
&lt;supplementary-material content-type=&quot;local-data&quot; id=&quot;f2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;media xlink:href=&quot;876316.f2.avi&quot; mimetype=&quot;video&quot; mime-subtype=&quot;x-msvideo&quot;&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click here for additional data file.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;/media&gt;
&lt;/supplementary-material&gt;
...</preformat>
        <p>Other articles, for example, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3656359"
            >PMC3656359</ext-link>, do not provide any content-related information in the
          captions:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;supplementary-material content-type=&quot;local-data&quot; id=&quot;SM1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;media xlink:href=&quot;43049_Jiang_Movie1.AVI&quot; mimetype=&quot;video&quot; mime-subtype=&quot;x-msvideo&quot;&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Click here for additional data file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;/media&gt;
&lt;/supplementary-material&gt;</preformat>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Missing references to supplementary materials</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>In a few cases, the source XML of suitably licensed articles available from PMC do not
          have any reference to the multimedia files whatsoever. For example <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=3104346"
            >PMC3104346</ext-link> has two supplemental videos, which can be viewed <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/8/59/787/suppl/DC1">on the
            publisher's site</ext-link>, but are not referenced in the XML.</p>
        <p>Another example of this is <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=3423924"
            >PMC3423924</ext-link>, which has a supplemental video that can be downloaded from the
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.hindawi.com/journals/ijad/2012/914947/sup/">publisher
            site</ext-link>, but, again, no reference to that from the XML.</p>


      </sec>
      <sec id='mt-pmc-efforts'>
        <title>Recent efforts at PMC</title>
        <p>Many of the problems described above were due to PMC's incorrectly adding @mimetype and
          @mime-subtype attributes to XML that it received, based on the assumption that the media
          file's extension accurately reflects its media type. When it was recognized that the
          filename extension was not a reliable indicator of the media type, and that it's better to
          have no declared media type than to have it wrong, PMC has stopped executing this
          function.</p>
        <p>Also, in part because of the recognition that the values for @mimetype and @mime-subtype
          being supplied by publishers was not reliable, PMC is in the process of changing the
          Tagging Guidelines to make these attributes, when they appear on the &lt;media&gt;
          element, optional.</p>
        <p>Also, in response to some of these problems, PMC has implemented a new feature in its
          rendering software to ensure the accuracy of the &quot;Content-type&quot; header it
          provides in response to HTTP requests for the media files. This makes use of the standard
          Unix library <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://netbsd.gw.com/cgi-bin/man-cgi?libmagic+3+NetBSD-current"
            >libmagic</ext-link>, which is also used by the OAMI and determines a file's type based
          on patterns of data within its content. In this way, PMC can be sure that it is delivering
          accurate metadata in the HTTP response, based on the actual file at the time it is
          served.</p>
        <p>There are no plans to retroactively fix the existing XML markup in the PMC database, or
          to adjust the @mimetype or @mime-subtype attributes for any new articles received.</p>


      </sec>
      <sec id='mt-standards'>
        <title>Standardization efforts</title>
        <p>Over the past few years, the NISO/NFAIS Supplemental Journal Article Materials Working
          Group has been working on standards for handling supplementary materials, and has
          published <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/rp-15-2013">NISO RP-15-2013, Recommended
            Practices for Online Supplemental Journal Article Materials</ext-link><xref
              ref-type="bibr" rid="r1"/> earlier this
          year.</p>
        <p>This document lists &quot;recommended minimal and extended metadata&quot; (section B.2.2
          Metadata Elements), and recommends open formats that can be rendered by free, open-source,
          and ubiquitous application software (section B.4.2 Preservation Recommendations) and also
          briefly touches upon licensing (section A.3.10 Rights Management). With respect to media
          types, the group recommends – as part of a strategy to enable long-term preservation –
          that publishers accept supplementary materials in formats defined in formal format
          registries, such as the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.udfr.org/"
            >Unified Digital Format Registry (UDFR)</ext-link> or <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM">PRONOM</ext-link>. These formats
          provide much more information than the simple media type.</p>
        <p>The kind of media type issues reported here would be much less frequent in articles
          properly tagged according to these NISO recommendations.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    
    <sec id='keywords'>
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <p>The OAMI, when it uploads files to Wikimedia Commons, assigns them to Wikimedia Commons
        categories, so as to facilitate search and discovery by users. The OAMI attempts to
        determine these categories based on keywords or subjects in the source XML, or MeSH terms
        supplied by the journal, by PMC or by PubMed for the corresponding article. We found that
        articles within the OA subset had very inconsistent tagging of keywords, and that caused
        many problems.</p>
      <p>The NISO JATS specification provides recommendations in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
          xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/0.4/n-pu72.html">Tagging
          Keywords</ext-link> section of each of the three tag sets. It describe two main methods
        for tagging keywords:</p>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <p>With any of a number of elements inside &lt;kwd-group&gt;: &lt;kwd&gt;,
            &lt;compound-kwd&gt;, &lt;compound-kwd-part&gt;, &lt;nested-kwd&gt;, and
            &lt;unstructured-kwd-group&gt;</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>With &lt;subject&gt; elements inside &lt;subj-group&gt;, inside
            &lt;article-categories&gt;</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>


      <sec id='tagging-kwd-fam'>
        <title>Tagging with kwd-family elements</title>
        <p>The &lt;kwd-group&gt; element is a container for other elements that specify the keywords
          themselves. It takes an attribute, @kwd-group-type, that qualifies the type of keywords
          that appear in the group. The JATS specification <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/1.0/?attr=kwd-group-type">page
            for this attribute</ext-link> indicates that it should be used for either of two
          purposes: defining the authority of a controlled vocabulary from which the keywords come,
          or for describing the type of the keywords as &quot;hierarchical&quot;,
          &quot;abbreviation&quot;, etc. (This is an unfortunate conflation of two orthogonal
          concepts.)</p>
        <p>The &lt;kwd-group&gt; element can appear within either article or section metadata.
          Unfortunately, at present, it cannot be applied to individual media or data files.
          However, there is a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.niso.org/apps/group_public/view_comment.php?comment_id=252"
            >comment on the NISO site</ext-link> requesting that this attribute be added to several
          other elements, including &lt;media&gt; and &lt;supplementary-material&gt;, and we support
          this suggestion.</p>
        <p>The following is an example of the typical usage of &lt;kwd-group&gt; and &lt;kwd&gt;,
          from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=2630158"
            >PMC2630158</ext-link>:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;kwd-group&gt;
  &lt;kwd&gt;French pox&lt;/kwd&gt;
  &lt;kwd&gt;Augsburg&lt;/kwd&gt;
  &lt;kwd&gt;medical semiotics&lt;/kwd&gt;
  &lt;kwd&gt;diagnosis&lt;/kwd&gt;
  &lt;kwd&gt;hospital&lt;/kwd&gt;
&lt;/kwd-group&gt;</preformat>


      </sec>
      <sec id='tagging-subject'>
        <title>Tagging with &lt;subject&gt;</title>
        <p>In many articles, keywords are tagged within &lt;subject&gt; elements, that are nested
          hierarchically inside &lt;subj-group&gt; elements.</p>
        <p>An example of reasonably good tagging is from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3708714"
            >PMC3708714</ext-link>, where the keywords are specified in a clean hierarchical
          structure inside &lt;subj-group&gt; and &lt;subject&gt; elements:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;subj-group subj-group-type=&quot;Discipline-v2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;subject&gt;Biology&lt;/subject&gt;
  &lt;subj-group&gt;
    &lt;subject&gt;Biophysics&lt;/subject&gt;
    &lt;subj-group&gt;
      &lt;subject&gt;Nucleic Acids&lt;/subject&gt;
      &lt;subj-group&gt;
        &lt;subject&gt;DNA&lt;/subject&gt;
      &lt;/subj-group&gt;
    &lt;/subj-group&gt;
  &lt;/subj-group&gt;
  &lt;subj-group&gt;
    &lt;subject&gt;Computational Biology&lt;/subject&gt;
    &lt;subj-group&gt;
      &lt;subject&gt;Molecular Genetics&lt;/subject&gt;
      &lt;subj-group&gt;
        &lt;subject&gt;Gene Regulation&lt;/subject&gt;
      &lt;/subj-group&gt;
    &lt;/subj-group&gt;
  &lt;/subj-group&gt;
  ...
  &lt;subj-group&gt;
    &lt;subject&gt;Synthetic Biology&lt;/subject&gt;
  &lt;/subj-group&gt;
&lt;/subj-group&gt;</preformat>


      </sec>
      <sec id='kw-problems'>
        <title>Tagging problems</title>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Bad keywords</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>Because the values for keywords are unconstrained, and typically not members of a
          controlled vocabulary, there is no way to validate them. This, of course, leads to
          problems with typos, misspellings, differences in case, and so forth, that make them
          difficult to process by machine.</p>
        <p>For example, we have noticed that in PLOS articles, a recurring typographical error is
          encountered, in which a superfluous space is inserted into a keyword. When media files
          from these articles are processed by the OAMI and uploaded to Wikimedia Commons, they are
          thus assigned the Wikimedia Commons category &quot;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Biophysic_al_simulations"
            >Biophysic al simulations</ext-link>&quot;. To work around this problem, we have
          inserted a permanent redirect from that misspelled category to one with the proper
          spelling. The presence of files in this redirected category then triggers another bot on
          Wikimedia Commons to fix the categorization of affected files automatically.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Inconsistent use of the @subj-group-type attribute</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>Most of the time, the &lt;subj-group&gt; and &lt;subject&gt; elements are used to
          specify, not keywords, but a subject heading that would appear in the Table of Contents
          for a journal issue; and is often equivalent to the type of article, as
          &quot;Article&quot;, &quot;Letter to Editor&quot;, &quot;Meeting Notice&quot;, etc. When
          used this way, the @subj-group-type attribute normally has the value
          &quot;heading&quot;.</p>
        <p>When using &lt;subj-group&gt; and &lt;subject&gt; elements to describe keywords, the JATS
          specification suggests that the @subj-group-type attribute have a value of, for example,
          &quot;keywords&quot;. However, we found the use of this attribute to be very inconsistent.
          Note in the &quot;good&quot; example above, that the value &quot;Discipline-v2&quot; is
          used. In a sample of articles from the OA subset, often we saw no value at all given for
          this attribute. Among those that did supply a value, we found the following:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Article Type</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Article type</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Primary</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Secondary</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>hw-coll-titles</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>hwp-journal-coll</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>overline</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>search-keyword</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>section</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>topic</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>As with the keyword values themselves, this proliferation of values, with no centralized
          way to determine their semantics, makes them difficult to process by machine.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>No keywords or subject tags</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>In many articles, no keywords or subject tags were given at all, other than the
          &quot;heading&quot; subject, which is not useful for this purpose. For example, <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/efetch.fcgi?db=pmc&amp;id=PMC3425056"
            >PMC3425056</ext-link> has only this markup:</p>
        <preformat>&lt;subj-group subj-group-type=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;
  &lt;subject&gt;Case Report&lt;/subject&gt;
&lt;/subj-group&gt;</preformat>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic>Inconsistent use of the @kwd-group-type attribute</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p>As with the @subj-group-type attribute described above (and most of the attributes
          defined in JATS), there is no enumeration of, or constraint on, the values that this
          attribute can take. Publishers each choose their own values, and this leads to
          incompatibilities.</p>
        <p>The following are some of the values that we found:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>abbr</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>author</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>journal subjects</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>KEYWORDS</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>keywords</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>kwd</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>



      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id='recommendations'>
      <title>Recommendations</title>
      <p>We will thus end by discussing some more long-term prospects for enhancing the
        discoverability of reuseable open-access content, combined with practical recommendations
        for how the current situation might be improved. </p>

      <sec id='rec-license'>
        <title>License tagging</title>
        <p>We recommend that the PMC Tagging Guidelines and Style Checker be changed to require
          that, if a license is defined by a URI (as are CC licenses), that the article
            <italic>must</italic> put this URL into the @xlink:href on the &lt;license&gt; element.
          This should be the sole place that a machine (or anyone) should need to look for the
          license URI. (This is in contrast to the current guidelines, which state that it can be
          tagged on an @xlink:href on either the &lt;license&gt; element, or on any &lt;ext-link&gt;
          descendent of &lt;license&gt;.)</p>
        <p>If that were implemented, then it would no longer be necessary to do comparisons between
          that URI and any other URI within the &lt;license-p&gt; elements, and this check should be
          dropped. The rationale for this is that any content within the &lt;license-p&gt; elements
          is intended for human, not machine, consumption, and might contain arbitrary hyperlinks,
          which cannot be predicted, and should not be constrained.</p>
        <p>The PMC Style Checker could be enhanced to dynamically check the validity of any
          creativecommons.org URIs that appear in that attribute. Creative Commons provides a web
          service for this purpose (see, for example, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://api.creativecommons.org/rest/dev/details?license-uri=http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/ca/"
            >this service call</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>Funders of scientific research that have open-access mandates might consider adding
          the requirement that the licenses be tagged according to the best practices
          described here.  That would facilitate automated tools that could verify that the
          work does, indeed, conform to their OA requirements.</p>
      </sec>
      
      <sec id='rec-pmc-license'>
        <title>PMC license metadata</title>
        <p>The license metadata for articles in the PMC archive, because it is based on the markup
          of the source XML, is not reliable. One effect of this, as discussed above, is that it
          detracts from the usefulness of the search-by-license feature.</p>
        <p>PMC could improve the way this license data is derived, re-using some of the business
          rules by which it determines which articles become part of the OA subset.</p>
        <p>Also, as part of this project, we curated the license data for thousands of articles in
          the PMC OA subset. It would be nice if PMC would incorporate that data back into their
          system, so that future users would not have to duplicate our effort.</p>
        <p>The license data that does reside in the PMC system should be better exposed. For
          example, we recommend that it be added to the E-utilities esummary output for articles,
          for both PubMed and PMC.</p>
        <p>For articles that have multiple licenses, which either change over time, or apply to
          different parts (for example, one license for the article proper, and another for data),
          we suggest that there be one &lt;license&gt; element for each, and that the @specific-use
          attribute be used to define the scope. The default scope would be &quot;article&quot;, but
          if, for example, there were a different license for the data, then that would be marked up
          as follows.</p>
        <preformat>&lt;permissions&gt;
  &lt;license license-type=&quot;open-access&quot;
           xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&quot;&gt;...&lt;/license&gt;
  &lt;license license-type=&quot;open-access&quot;
           specific-use=&quot;scope: data&quot;
           xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/&quot;&gt;...&lt;/license&gt;
&lt;/permissions&gt;</preformat>
        <p>If the article has a license that changes over time, then that could be marked up as
          follows (this is meant to be suggestive, only).</p>
        <preformat>&lt;permissions&gt;
  &lt;license license-type=&quot;open-access&quot;
           specific-use=&quot;end-date: 2013-10-22&quot;
           xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&quot;&gt;...&lt;/license&gt;
  &lt;license license-type=&quot;open-access&quot;
           specific-use=&quot;start-date: 2013-10-23&quot;
           xlink:href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/&quot;&gt;...&lt;/license&gt;
&lt;/permissions&gt;</preformat>
      </sec>

      <sec id='rec-mt'>
        <title>Media types and format</title>
        <p>The PMC Tagging Guidelines should be changed to require the media types to be in the
          @mimetype attribute only, and deprecate @mime-subtype. The Style Checker should verify
          that the @mimetype attribute is present, that it has a valid form, and that @mime-subtype
          is not given.</p>
        <p>PMC could develop a media type checking utility, using the same libmagic Unix library and
          data files, to be applied to data and media files that accompany articles for ingest. The
          system could fix the @mimetype attributes in the source XML to reflect the actual media
          types as determined by this library. As mentioned above, PMC has fixed the HTTP
          &quot;content-type&quot; headers, but if someone were to download the article and
          accompanying media files, and share them outside of the PMC system, the mismatch in the
          source XML could still be a problem.</p>
        <p>Perhaps this utility could also function to validate the multimedia and other data files
          that are received. Since these files form an integral part of the scientific record, just
          as with the source XML, the validity of these files is important. Since the operation of
          the OAMI began, we have found on the order of 100 video files which could not be
          processed, because some essential information (for example, the frame rate, or
          intermediate I-frames) is not given, or not in a proper way (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.plosone.org/annotation/listThread.action?root=65463"
            >example</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>Such a data validation system could start with a small set of file types, for which
          consistency checks could be set up. The consistency checker could be made available as a
          web service, and the Tagging Guidelines could recommend (but not require) that files be
          provided in those formats, and link to the web service.</p>
        <p>As mentioned above, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.niso.org/apps/group_public/download.php/10055/RP-15-2013_Supplemental_Materials.pdf"
            >NISO RP-15-2013</ext-link> has recently been published, and we encourage publishers to
          adopt these recommendations. We note that there is another paper within these conference
          proceedings, &quot;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/jats-con/2013/schedule2013a.html#2-900">Extending
            JATS to include the NISO/NFAIS Recommended Practices for Online Supplemental Journal
            Article Materials</ext-link>&quot;, which might prove useful in this regard.</p>
        <p>However, we would also like to note that we have concerns about these recommendations,
          that mirror some of the concerns that we have expressed about JATS in general.
          Specifically, we feel that the recommendations are, in many cases, not conducive to
          producing consistent, robust, and machine readable metadata.</p>
        <p>For example, in the description of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://supplemental.niso.org/tag-library/index.html?elem=license"
            >&lt;license&gt;</ext-link> element, they say, &quot;The &lt;ext-link&gt; can be used to
          link to licenses that are already defined, such as a Creative Commons license.&quot; This
          should not be discretionary. The specification should be explicit that when a URI exists
          that identifies a license, that it must be included, and in a well-defined place. Note
          that this schema allows multiple &lt;ext-link&gt; elements under &lt;license&gt;, so the
          ambiguities that exist in JATS, that have led to such wide variation in tagging of this
          metadata, are continued in this new recommendation.</p>
      </sec>

      <sec id='rec-kw'>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <p>As mentioned above, we support the suggestion on the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.niso.org/apps/group_public/view_comment.php?comment_id=252">NISO
            JATS document page</ext-link> requesting that the &lt;kwd-group&gt; element be added to
          the content model of several new elements, including &lt;media&gt; and
          &lt;supplementary-material&gt;.</p>
      </sec>

      <sec id='rec-pub-versioning'>
        <title>Public versioning of PMC/OA XML files</title>
        <p>Many of the issues discussed here could in principle be fixed by running some dedicated
          scripts over the affected XML files. However, even if such scripts were functional and
          readily available, there is currently no mechanism that would allow such fixes to be fed
          back systematically and automatically to the respective sources of these XML files, or to
          third-party copies thereof. One step in this direction would be to make the XML files
          available in an updatable environment with public versioning. This would be possible for
          articles in the Open Access Subset. Indeed, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="https://github.com/elifesciences/elife-xml">eLife</ext-link> and <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/pensoft">Pensoft</ext-link> have
          demoed this on GitHub, and a tool for <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="https://github.com/konrad/JATS-to-Mediawiki">porting JATS XML to MediaWiki
            environments</ext-link> exists as well.</p>
        <p>Various kinds of modifications to existing XML are theoretically plausible that would
          merit adoption of such a system. These include – but are not limited to – typos,
          corrigenda and retractions, but also license changes (e.g. when copyright owner changes
          licensing backwards, or when copyright expires), media type mismatches, missing or mixed
          up files, captions or unique identifiers, or &quot;in press&quot; references.</p>
      </sec>

      <sec id='rec-use-cases'>
        <title>Use cases</title>
        <p>So far, JATS has mainly been used to exchange information between publishers and
          archives. Under traditional notions of copyright, large-scale reuse of such information by
          third parties is very limited but PMC's Open Access Subset – particularly the
          Wikimedia-compatibly licensed portions thereof – opens the door for experimentation on
          this front. We see value here in introducing the concept of use cases and collaborating
          with suitable use case partners in further developing JATS as well as the corresponding
          guidelines and style checkers. The OAMI bot could serve as one such use case. <ext-link
            ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-11-85">Species
            disambiguation</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/asi.20707">citation analyses</ext-link> or
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/10101/npre.2010.4267.2"
            >automated query formulation</ext-link> could be others.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>

  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id='r1'>
        <mixed-citation>
          <collab>National Information Standards Organization (NISO)</collab>
          <source>RP-15-2013 Recommended Practices for Online Supplemental Journal Article
            Materials</source>.
          <year>2013</year> <month>Jan</month>.
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
            xlink:href="http://www.niso.org/apps/group_public/download.php/10055/RP-15-2013_Supplemental_Materials.pdf"
            >http://www.niso.org/apps/group_public/download.php/10055/RP-15-2013_Supplemental_Materials.pdf</ext-link>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
